Well, speaking of the northern area, the population that left Barra Funda
Bom, ainda na Zona norte esta população que sai da Barra funda,
and the downtown areas started to build other spaces, other territories:
que sai uma parte do centro também,
Casa Verde, Peruche, and Brasilândia. They're also territories of blacks.
Casa verde, Peruche, que também são territórios negros, a Brasilândia é um território negro.
Another share of that population went to the southern region,
A gente também tem outra frente que vai sentido a Zona Sul:
to the Jabaquara neighbourhood, another important territory of blacks.
Jabaquara é um importante território negro,
Historically, the Jabaquara quilombo was based on it...
que historicamente abrigou o quilombo do Jabaquara...
And... well, what about it? It had a very, very complicated history.
Bom, sobre o quilombo do Jabaquara é uma história muito complicada, né?
It's hard to recognize the history of a place, isn't it?
É difícil reconhecer a história do lugar, né?
There's a political purpose in the construction of history.
A construção da história também é política, né?
Where today is Sítio da Ressaca House was once the Jabaquara quilombo.
Onde hoje é a casa do Sítio da Ressaca era o quilombo do Jabaquara.
You may find it odd, "a quilombo in the middle of the city?"
“Mas um quilombo no meio da cidade de São Paulo?”
The Saracura quilombo was located here too!
Tinha o quilombo da Saracura!
It was the first urban quilombo of Sao Paulo.
Foi o primeiro quilombo urbano de São Paulo.